你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院
welcome to pwn college
我是Yan，在今天的视频中
I am Yan and today in this video
我们将讨论汇编中的环境交互
we're going to be talking about environment interaction in assembly
上节课我们以这个问题收尾
so in the last lecture we end up with this question
程序如何退出
how the hell do we quit
退出是与操作系统的一个交互
well quitting your program is a interaction with your operating system
我这里说的与操作系统交互实际是指
and then really this what I mean operating system interactions here
通过操作系统与环境进行交互
you interact with the environment through an operating system
那么我们怎么退出呢
so how do we exit
你可以用系统调用
well you use something called a system call
不光是退出程序
you use it not just to exit
你可以用它来做任何不是原始计算的事情
you use it to do anything that is not raw computation
系统调用类似call指令
a system call is just like a call instruction
除了
except for instead of
这么说有问题
well I mean that's very false
但概念上
but conceptually
它不是跳转到你程序内的某处
instead of jumping elsewhere in your program
而是跳转到操作系统
it jumps to the operating system
操作系统会处理它
and the operating system handles it
操作系统会协调程序与环境其余部分的交互
the operating system mediates your program's interaction with the rest of the environment
以后的模块中，我们会深入研究操作系统
and we're going to get really really deep into this operating system crap in the future module
但是现在
but for now
我们要知道的是
what we want to understand is that
你能通过系统调用和操作系统交互
you interact with that operating system using a system call
你已经了解到了一些系统调用
and you've learned about system calls
你已经执行过一些系统调用
you've performed some system calls
像read、write，耳熟吧
read write sounds familiar
在之前的模块中用过
from previous modules
现在我们要用在汇编中使用它们
well now we're going to do them in assembly
它非常简单
and it's super simple
你只需要调用syscall指令
you just call the syscall instruction
在此之前，将rax设置为一个值
and you set RAX to a magic value
即选择要执行的系统调用
that is select the syscall you want to perform
然后设置参数
then you set the arguments
设置RDI，第一个参数
set the arguments in RDI first argument
RSI，第二参数
RSI second argument
RDX，第三个参数，目前很熟悉
RDX third argument sound familiar so far
这和调用函数一样
this is the same as calling functions
但接下来的三个是不同的，或者其中的一些
but the next 3 are different or some of them
所以请记住
so just keep in mind
第四个参数是r10
fourth arguments are r10
你需要系统调用号
you need the syscall number
read的系统调用号是0
the syscall number for read is 0
write的系统调用号是2
syscall number for write is 2
在调用syscall之前
right before calling syscall
要把rax设为这个值
just set rax to that value
抱歉，1代表write
sorry 0 and 1 for write
如果你感兴趣的话
if you are interested
你会需要这个的
well you will need this
Ryan A Chapman维护了一个64位x86的Linux系统调用表
Ryan A Chapman maintains a Linux system call table for a 64 bit x86
不管我搜的是什么，答案总碰巧在这里
happens to be the top result for whatever search I usually do
现在我都直接在它里面搜索了
and it has gone to the point where my search is now Ryan A Chapman
网上还有其他系统调用表
there are other syscall tables on the internet
dojo中该模块的介绍里也有
and in the module details on the dojo
但
but
在这里
here
我将在这节课中举3个系统调用做为例子
I'm going to give an example of in this lecture 3 system calls
第一个
first
甚至更多
maybe even more
第一个就是read
the first one will be read
所以我们要调用
so we're going to call
我应该把这个放在这里
and I should actually probably have this here
我们会调用
but we're gonna call
为什么现在不放呢
actually why don't I put this on here
等一下
wait one second
好多了
better slide
我们从标准输入读入100字节到栈
so we're gonna read 100 bytes from standard input to the stack
你可能已经在程序交互模块中做过了
now you have done this in program interaction probably
你可能这样调用的，read
you've probably called read
0表示标准输入
0 for standard input
buff是你在局部变量中定义的缓冲区
buff some buffer you defined live in local variable
它在栈上
guess what that lives on the stack
然后100
你用它来读入flag
to read in your flag
或者从标准输入中读取
or well to read an input from the standard input whatever
然后把结果放进一个叫n的变量里
and you put the result in a variable called n
汇编大致是这样的
this looks roughly like this
先mov rdi, 0
you move rdi 0
这是系统调用的第一个参数
that's the first argument to the syscall
RSI是第二个参数
RSI is the second argument
你把它设为rsp
you set it to the stack pointer
RDX是100，表示你要读入多少
RDX is 100 how much you're going to read
RAX为0，表示read的系统调用号
RAX is 0 the syscall number of read
执行syscall
syscall
就read了
boom you've read
系统调用返回值放到RAX
syscall returns into RAX
rax中是实际读取的字节数
the number of bytes read
然后调用write把读到的写到标准输出
and then you call write to write that into standard out
将RDI设置为标准输出
again set RDI to standard out
RSI设为rsp
RSI to the stack
这步你不需要重做
and you don't have to redo this
RSI没被修改
RSI isn't clobber
但，其它情况可能会被改
but it you know could be potentially in other exotic cases
把rax赋值给RDX
you move rax into RDX
rax中装的read的返回值
rax there again the return value of read
即实际读取的字节数
how many bytes were actually read
然后将系统调用号设为write对应的
and then you set the syscall number to write and
触发系统调用
trigger a system call
read，write，2个系统调用了
boom read write two system calls
有很多系统调用
there's a lot of system calls
有超过300个系统调用
there is just an absolutely enormous over 300 syscalls
他们能做很多不同的事情
they do a lot of different stuff
我相信这些你都用过了
I'm sure you've used by now all of these
在程序交互模块中
in program interaction
至少大部分都用过了
or at least most of them
他们可能看起来非常熟悉
they probably look horrifyingly familiar
现在
now
看一下这个open
look at this open guy
调用它需要一个字符串
call it takes a string
它需要一个实际的路径
calls like it takes an actual path
比如/flag之类的
like /flag for example or something
现在
now
字符串，如路径，占用一段连续的内存
a string like a path is a continuous set of bytes in memory
对于字符串，是ASCII字节码，ASCII编码
for strings its ASCII bytes encoded in ASCII
末尾是一个0字节
followed by a 0 byte
它表示结束
that says hey we're done
大概几个模块以后
now later on a couple modules around
你会看到这是一个坏主意
you'll see all the various ways this is a bad idea
事实上，你知道吗
in fact you know what
所有的计算都是一个坏主意
all of computing is a bad idea
因为计算机
because of computing
这鬼东西发明出来的几十年后
decades after this awesome whatever inventions of cool stuff
大半夜的，我还在给大家录视频
recording videos for everybody in the middle of the night
不然我可能在睡觉
I could be sleeping
但没关系
but it's okay
我喜欢制作教育材料，希望这对你们有用
I love bringing educational material and hopefully this is useful
我们来讨论一下如何在栈上构建这个字符串
let's talk about building this string on the stack
然后调用open打开一个文件
and then calling open to open a file
你可以一个字节一个字节得往栈上放
you can build a string on the stack by moving a bunch of single bytes
但还有更好的方法
and there are better ways to do it
我们会在其他模块中讨论它们
later on we talk about them in another modules for example
你会发现更好的方法
and you'll discover better ways to do it
但现在你可以简单得这样做
but you can just do it as simple as this
你往rsp+1放一字节数据
you move into RSP+1
哦
oops
应该是RSP
that should be RSP
我马上就回来
I'll be right back
回来了
we're back
放一字节到RSP指向的内存
so you move into RSP
放到rsp指向的栈内存
into the memory pointed by RSP and onto the stack
这会被解析
and this gets interpreted
我的意思是这些会当作ASCII码解析
I mean these gets interpreted as ASCII
会填入正确的ASCII码
the correct values are added
这就是汇编中的单引号的作用
because that's what the single quote does in assembly
你的栈中有2f 66 6c 61 67 00
and you got 2f 66 6c 61 67 00 in your stack
你可以用它来打开/flag
okay then you can just use that to open /flag
你
you move
正如这儿看到的，open需要一个路径和一个标志参数
open takes a as we saw here a path and a flags
所以我们要把标志设置为0
so we're going to set the flags to 0
接下来我会告诉你怎么做
and I'll tell you how to get that next
我们要把第一个参数设为内存中的/flag字符串
but we're going to set the first argument to this string in memory that says /flag
第二个参数设为0
second argument 0
open的系统调用号是2
the syscall number of open is 2
然后我们触发系统调用
and we hit syscall
打开文件
and we open our file
然后将文件描述符放到rax
and get the file descriptor number in RAX
酷
super cool okay
我们怎么得到这些常量
how do we get these constants these numbers
这真让人头疼
now this is a pain in the butt
有些系统调用
some system calls just have
需要知道一些，比如
like archaic sort of things you gotta know like
0 表示以只读模式打开
0 is how you open something in read only mode
只写，好像是1
and write only maybe is one
我不清楚
I don't know
你得查一下
you'll have to look it up
你可以写一个C程序来查
you can write a C program to do it
这是一个C程序，包含
so this is a C program that includes the
这些是man手册中关于这些标志的介绍
this is from the manpage that there're these flags
man手册中open的介绍
the manpage of open
你可以包含对应的头文件
you can include the right things
然后写一个程序把它打印出来
and then just write a program that printfs it
然后运行它
and run it
它说，O_RDONLY是0，祝你好运
and it says oh O_RDONLY is 0 good luck
好了
there you go
现在终于
now finally
我们可以退出了
we can quit and rest
这个，把42放入rdi
this moves 42 into RDI
这将是程序的返回码
that's going to be the return code of the program
会给到调用它的bash
for your bash scripts that call it
我们将rax置为60
we're going to move 60 to rax
这是exit的系统调用号
that's the syscall number of exit
我们调用syscall
and we call syscall
然后程序就没了
and the program goes away
它退出了
it quits
这就是与操作系统交互的方式
so the way to interact with the operating system
一会我们谈谈如何编译
now let's talk about actually building this stuff
以及调试
debugging it and so on next